<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mount Moriah, or A sermon preached at Carrick, by Mr. Riddale, August 5. 1679.</title>
            <author>Riddale, Archibald.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04998</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182718</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981699</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180311</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04998)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180311)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2825:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mount Moriah, or A sermon preached at Carrick, by Mr. Riddale, August 5. 1679.</title>
                  <author>Riddale, Archibald.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks all after p. 16; stained, print show-through with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXI, 10 --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Covenanters --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180311:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Mount Moriah: OR, A SERMON Preached at <hi>Carrick,</hi> By Mr. Riddale, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 5. 1679.</head>
            <p>MAy not ſay to you, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid to his father, <hi>There is wood, and here is the Fire, but where is the Lamb?</hi> Here is a goodly Company gathered together from ſeveral places, and that with ſome outward preſentation and appearance of Zeal for the Cauſe of God, in caſe of neceſſity we moſt commend that ſight; but there is one thing wanting, a Communicating frame, yet here is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendency of our God, that hath ſent forth Meſſengers, who have opened the Windows of Heaven. Sirs, what have you been doing to a Crucified Buried Chriſt, who has been wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of the Grave, many are ſtriving to keep him farther in the Grave, both by Friends and Foes, nothing wanting on their part: Many are expecting that the Communicants of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180311:2"/>
               <hi>Carrick</hi> ſhould help Chriſt out of the Grave; theſe whoſe hearts are bleeding, who could not get here, are expecting that the Communicants ſhould help the Cauſe, and its lying upon your ſhoulders, and therefore expect ye ſhould lend them a lift in the day of their diſtreſs; but for any thing I can ſay, there is a New Stone laid upon Chriſts Grave; Oh Sirs! do you think that Jeſus who has ſo many Crucifying him this day, that ye ſhould come in among the reſt; do you think that Jeſus who has ſo many Crucifying him this day, that ye ſhould come in among the reſt: do you think that all the Prelates and Counſellors are not able to do it? will you give him a blow, and make him take his farwell? Its his friends who are now his Crucifyers; be ſerious then that matters come not to that height as that ye ſpit upon Chriſts face. I wot well he has teſtifyed his good will to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions hitherto, and many a ſweet manifeſtation of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence has been ſeen amongſt them. Is God then weary of entertaining, no, no, no, but the often budding upon us of the new Wine of Heaven, hath made it change its taſte, and become loathſome, and its juſt with God to ſend now a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſpean us a Seaſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180311:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 81. and 10. at the cloſe.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Open thy Mouth wide, and I will fill it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>By the providence and good hand of our God, all that hath been Preached yet, hath hitherto been much to this purpoſe, to ſet you on work for a Communion, to receive a Feaſt at the hand of the Lord. It may be there hath been ſuch rich offers already, that any offer that I can make at this time, may be but loathſome to you. However, that is the thing that we purpoſe at preſent, that Communicants ſhould open their mouths wide. This was his Exhortation in theſe words that we have read; and that it may be the more taking, he Prefaces this to it, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, that brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Egypt; both that relation that is between you and me, ſhould engage you to liſten the better to my offer, for as much as there is a ſtanding Covenant between you and me, ſhould engage you to liſſen the better to my offer, for as much as there is a ſtanding Covenant between you and me, <hi>Ye are my people, and I am your God.</hi> And likewiſe the many courteſies and favours that I have done to you already, the good turns that I have wrought for you when ye were in Bondage, and under the Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Satan, and under the power of your own Luſts; and ye might have been ſwallowed up in the midſt of your difficulties, when there was none to ſee to you, nor to help you at all. I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on you, and gave you relief; this is expreſſed by his bringing them out of the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> it is a Metaphorical expreſſion bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from that ſignal deliverence that the Lord gave to his Church when he brought them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with a high hand, as it was ſet down according to the Ten Commandements at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> that it may have weight to garr folk take heed to their way before God: <hi>Lord thy God that brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Egypt: Now I here make a rich offer of the Goſpel to you, and all that I deſire at your hand is, but that ye will receive that which I will give, and that on cheap and eaſie terms, and a large offer it is, and I crave no more at your hands but this, open but ye your mouths, and open them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180311:3"/>wide, and ye ſhall not want that that ſhall make you up for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. I ſuppoſe it is evident to you all, that the Lord means not here the mouth of the body, and it is to that that he purpoſes earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly priviledges, and earthly advantages, and that is the way that he takes with his Dogs, that he puts at the back of the door, that is the Hypocrites Portion, and the portion of him that hath his allowance in the world; but that that he means, is the opening of the mouth of the Soul, and the mouth of the Heart, to receive ſpiritual bleſſings and ſpiritual allowances, that is all the purpoſe of this liberal King, that gives liberally to all, and upbraids none; he does indeed require the opening of the mouth to God in a Communion, to receive the Elements that he purpoſes, but that is only to make way for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of that that is more worth, and that comes clad under that outward ſhape, that is the Sacrament, but the thing ſignified is the main thing Chriſt himſelf, and the benefits of the New Covenant, that is it the Lord fills the mouth of his people. Now then, your duty that I require at your hands, is that ye open your mouths wide, and the priviledges that comes on the back of this duty is, I will fill theſe mouths of yours if ye will open them never ſo wide; there ſhall not be a lirk in them all, but they ſhall be filled up. Now I muſt firſt explain in this, what is the import of the word, <hi>Open your Mouths wide;</hi> there is four things comprehended under it. 1. There is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended one and great ſenſe of Folks need and want of the priviledges of the Goſpel; the mouth is half opened when a perſon wins to travel in the exerciſe of his own wants and ſenſe: Indeed they that want a ſenſe of the real neceſſity lying upon them, they are not the folk that ſhall come ſpeed at the Kings hand; but they that receive of him, is ſuch as lays this as the foundation ſtone of the works; I am a poor, indigent, and needy creature, I am undone if I get not ſomething, this is pointed out in the exerciſe of the poor things that come to Chriſt when he travelled in the world; ſome comes in the ſenſe of their blindneſs, and ſome in the ſenſe of their lameneſs, and ſome came in the ſenſe of their blindneſs, and ſome in the ſenſe of this, that the Devil behoved to be caſt out of them, and that they were undone, if they got not theſe things done: This made <hi>Barti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus</hi> cry, this made the Woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> cry, ſenſe of need that they were within a hair-breadth of Hell; if God had not Mercy on them, there is nothing for me, but I will periſh and be undone for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180311:3"/>even, and I will travel under the power of my luſts, a ſtranger to the grace of God, if thou were never ſo far been in Religion, O commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant, it ſets thee to Travel in the ſenſe of thy wants, for there is none here but they ſtand in need of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly</hi> The opening of the mouth wide, Comprehends a right Senſe of the excellency and worth of theſe priviledges that our Lord holds out ſuch a ſence of their excellency, as doth darken all earthly privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and all advantages, a ſence of their excellency that would cauſe you to cry with <hi>Paul</hi> the 3 of <hi>Philipians,</hi> I count all things loſs and dung, that I may win Chriſt, and with <hi>David</hi> in the 73 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> whom have I in Heaven but thee, and on the earth that I deſire beſide thee: and the poor thing is put to that with it, it is grace that I muſt have, it is Chriſt that I muſt have; every drop of mercy is more ſweet then the Honey, and the Honey-Comb: the word of God was ſweet to <hi>David,</hi> that was the opening of his Mouth, and he reckoned Goſpel priviledges ſo ſweet, that he could eaſily forgo all to be at it: he envyed the Sparrow and the Swallow that bigged their Neſts in the Tabernacle of God, and chuſeth rather to be a door Keeper in the Houſe of God, then to dwell in the Tents of wickeneſs, that is the opening of the mouth; then the Soul cryed none but Chriſt, none but Chriſt, and give me all the pleaſures is the World I will deſpiſe them, on this account it is ſome that is excellent and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious that I muſt have.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> The opening of the Mouth wide comprehends a large and inſatiable deſire after the Lord; it is not enough that the perſon cry out under his want, and that the man know the excellency of Chriſt; but there is this needful and ardent deſire to beat-it, ſuch a reſolution as is in the 132 <hi>Pſalm.</hi> I ſwear to the Lord, that I will not go to my Bed, that I will not give reſt to mine Eyes, nor ſlumber to mine Eye-Lids, till I prepare a place to the Lord: he will not be tangled with other difficulties that is in the wav, but he muſt be at Chriſt, and he reſolves, that although he ſhould break his Neck be the gate, he ſhall have him: he has alonging for a ſight of him, it is no ſtrange thing when <hi>David</hi> in the 12 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> cryes as the heart panteth after the water Brooks, ſo my heart panteth after thee: my Soul thirſts for the Living God, and in the 63 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> my heart and Fleſh cryed out for the Living God, ſuch a deſire after him would be the opening of a mouth to God, on the back, of a Communion.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180311:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:180311:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180311:5"/>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4ly,</hi> The opening of the mouth wide, comprehends a prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and making ready the Soul for Chriſt; the man that opens his mouth makes ready to receive his Food; the man that opens his mouth makes all ready, and when Chriſt ſays, give me thy Heart, he is willing to give him it, that is the equivalent of this, he will have the heart in a ſuitable dreſs and ready for him; are ye ſuitable Communicants, the day the heart muſt be in a right frame, and their is four things requiſite for the preparing of the heart that is comprehended under the opening of the mouth to receive the priviledges.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is required for the preparing of the heart to have a ſuitable exerciſe, a Travelling through matters between God and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to ſee how they ſtand, it is required of a communicant that he muſt examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread and drink of that Cup; he that comes with a ſuitable Frame, his Mouth is opened; thus ſaith the Lord, conſider your ways, conſider your ways: you moſt Travel through matters between God and you, and you muſt know in what Tearms yee ſtand with him, what Length have yee won, how is your Spirits diſpoſed for ſuch work on the Lords day; how ſtand yee affected to your King and Husband, that you are to ſhake hands with, what think yee of the bargain between him and you, that he will be a husband to you, that he ſhould ſee to you, and have a deſire of you, that yee ſhall truſt your caſe to him, and that ye ſhall wait on him in Death and in Life, and that death it ſelf ſhall not part you and him, if yee ſhould go to a Burning Fire with him, yee will not part with him, if yee ſhould Travell to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains with him, ye will not part with him, if yee ſhould go Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of <hi>Scotland</hi> with him, yee will not part with him: once be clear, for you muſt not come and make a blind bargain.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> A ſecond thing that is requiſite for the preparing of the heart for Chriſt, is to get all theſe evils and abominations to the door that uſes to take up his room, and that hinders his heartſome entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and dwelling there, there is a task for a Communicant to ſweep the houſe, and open the everlaſting door, and to caſt wide the Gate that the King of Glory may come in, that is the opening of the mouth to God to put ſtrangers to the door thou that has entertained Chriſt, he being in thy boſome, thou muſt give a farewell to all drunkards, and to whore-maſtering the old trade, thou muſt take farewell of it,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180311:5"/>ye that loved the World and eaſe better than Chriſt; ye muſt bid farewell to them, and ye muſt ſay as <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſays in the laſt of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea, What have I any more to do with Idols?</hi> Thou that loved thy ſelf better than Chriſt, thou muſt ſay, ſhall I put my ſelf in his room? nay, thou muſt take thy ſelf and thy right hand that has offended thee, and thy eye that his offended thee, and thou muſt tread un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot, if it were even thy moſt precious enjoyments and delights; you muſt take your farewell of them, for Chriſt cannot take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the heart, nor can ye open the mouth, till theſe things get a farewell, that muſt be your exerciſe the day: O communicants, ye muſt go through your pride, and your vanity, and your looſeneſs, and your own unrighteouſneſs, and ſelf love, ye muſt go through them one after another, and put them to the door, and ſay, what have I to do with thee any more? that is, to prepare thy heart for Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly,</hi> A third thing required in preparing the heart for Jeſus Chriſt, is this, there muſt be a working up the heart to a heavenly frame; it is not every frame that will pleaſe him for a Communion frame, it muſt be a Heavenly frame, that is, a frame that will pleaſe him, and that is a frame that is made up of many frames; tenderneſs is required here, ſenſe of ſin is required here, and ſelf-denyal is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red here, ſelf-loathing is required here, that a heavenly frame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends; the fear of God muſt be there, to come trembling and quaking to the Ordinances of Chriſt, to have love burning as a coal within thy breaſt, to be content to do any thing, that Chriſt may be glorified and magnified; theſe things is required to a heavenly frame, and that muſt be to make the houſe ready, and the mouth opened wide for the Son of God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4ly,</hi> A fourth thing required in the preparing of the heart, is a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful welcoming, and a chearful imbracing of any offer that Chriſt give you of any meat that he brings with him; indeed, the Chriſtian that opens his mouth wide, that is ſqueamiſh ſtomaked, he will not take every thing for the Worſhip of God, but will be tender there, and he will not take every thing for Ordinance, but if it be a dry morfel.</p>
            <p>I reſolve for a dry Morſel if it come out of Chriſts hand that will be ſweet, a right reliſhing of what ever he has that comes from Chriſt, though it ſhould be bitter and diſpleaſing to Fleſh and Blood, it may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180311:6"/>be the Lord will fill the Communicants of <hi>Carrick.</hi> with nothing but reproof, and he will ſay that is all I have to give you, the day I am angry at your wickedneſs, and I am angry at your baſeneſs, and ye muſt welcome ſuch a dinner if it were but a reproof, if it were but a Frown, and if it were but an affliction that is bitter to the Spirit yee muſt welcome it, if it were a croſs, and if it were to tell you the day yee muſt cr'e long ſuffer, yee muſt Seal theſe Truths with your Blood, if it were to reſolve to ſee your Husbands Head, hap for this work, reſolve to hear the news that your Husbands Carcaſs ſhall fall on the Top of the Mountains to be meat for Doggs, and the Fowls, and if it were to tell you that yee muſt goe to the Priſon the next day, and that is all yee will get; but if yce be right, yee muſt welcome all Chriſts allowances, be it ſweet or be it ſour; it may be ſome of you ſhall not have the promiſe the day of clearing of your Intereſt, but it may be yee will get that will cauſe you to go home weeping and Mourning, you muſt welcome it if your hearts be right oppened this day, yee will be made to ſee, let Chriſt give me what he will, if it be his allowance, I deſire to welcome him and it both; as to the priviledge I need not ſtand upon it, I will fill it, there is no great task, as if he had ſaid, that I do require at your hand, it coſt your Maſter another thing; it put your bleſſed Lord to Swim the Sea of wrath, and it put him to Travel through the Fire of Gods anger, and it put him before the Axe and Hammer of the Juſtice of God, and to let Juſtice lay on what ſtroaks he pleaſed, but as for you, you come eaſily by it, it is only to open the mouth, O that he purchaſed at ſuch a rate, he comes to you for nothing, but open your mouths wide and receive it, it is true, ye will may be Travel for it, and it is true ye will ſuffer for it, but what is that being weighted in the ballance of the Sanctuary, it is open, it as wide as ye will, and the more wide it be, the more acceptable to me: there is two things that I ſhall ſpeak of here.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Yee ſee the holy Ghoſt does ſuppoſe there is ſome Folks that does not open the mouth to theſe Goſpel priviledges, does all the World receive them now? does all the world open their mouths? no, no, their would not need ſuch intreaty to open their mouths, if it were but ſo read a little further in the Pſalm, and you will ſee that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment yee give him, the next word is, my People would not hearken to my voice; <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have none of me, oft-times he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180311:6"/>brings his rich, rare, precious Priviledges, but not received. Two conſiderations to clear this, 1. The many different complaints made by our Lord in offering them, as when tears came over his cheeks when looking to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> 2. What means ſo many running to the Ale-houſes, and ſo many ſleeping at Communions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preface before the Tables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do ye know this day, that our Bleſſed Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is King of <hi>Sion?</hi> do ye know that it is he that ye have to do with this day, not only a Jealous God, but it is the ſame Lord Jeſus that has help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many a poor creature that has Triumphed in the world, and has carryed in many a Fleece to Glory, that ſome time a day was as far aback from Heaven as ye are, that has rejoyced in bringing in poor ſinners to himſelf, and making way for their wellfare; and its that ſame Lord Jeſus that is this day treading upon the necks of Devils, that is this day tormenting many a Man or Woman in Hell; it is that ſame Lord Jeſus that has ſtained his Rayment with the Blood of his Enemies, and has refuſed Salvation to many a Countrey-ſide, and has refuſed the offers of mercy to many Men and Women up and down the world; it is he that is come to <hi>Carrick</hi> this day; it is he that is travelling among you, and behold he comes bringing Salvation with him, and we muſt ſay it, behold he comes meek and lowly, riding on an Aſs, and a Coalt the Foal of an Aſſe, and his bowels this day are yearning on you that are here; it is he that hath prepared a Feaſt a Feaſt of Fat things, of Wine on the Lees well refined; and O but he ſhowes bowels, and O but he ſhowes much tenderneſs, and O but he ſhowes much kindneſs in the day he provides a Feaſt for poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for his poor afflicted people; he knew very well that we could not live without him, he knew we had periſhed, if he had not once expoſed himſelf to Death on our behalf; and he knew very well, that we had but ſtarved, if he had not been given now and then a Feaſt: Now, that <hi>Scotland</hi> may not Starve amidſt all the ſad deſigns of our Enemies, not to have us ſtarved out of hand, and that we may not periſh in the midſt of the ſad deſigns and contrivances of our Enemies; he has this day prepared this allowance for you, and it is you that he is calling to open your mouths wide, that he may fill them in ſign and token, that he will be as good as his word, in ſatisfying the neceſſities of the hungry; he has given us this Ordinance that is of his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. And now Sirs, you muſt not think in the beginning of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180311:7"/>work, that our bleſſed Lord Jeſus allows theſe holy things to be caſten to Dogs, and that he allows ſuch Pearls to be caſten before Swine; it is every one that will get them this day, that he will admit to be partaker of the inheritance above; many are called, but few are choſen.</p>
            <p>Now more particularly, I ſerve an Inhibition this day againſt all Atheiſts that is here, that owns another God beſides the true God, and againſt all Idolaters, that turn the Worſhip of God into a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious form, or takes another Saviour beſides Chriſt, or that worſhips God in away that he has never preſcribed nor appointed.</p>
            <p>I muſt ſerve inhibition againſt all Curſers and Swearers, and ſuch as take the name of God in vain in their months, and all groſs Oaths, not only theſe that have horrid Curſes and execrations, or that will Curſe the People of God, and Work of God, but they that come out with minch't Oaths, were they never ſo ſmall, I ſerve an Inhibition upon all Sabbath breakers this day, ſuch as make not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Sanctifing all Gods ordinances, ſuch as make not conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of keeping Gods day, that dare bourd with any work upon Gods day, that Folk ſhould only do on an ordinary day, if it were but to look needleſsly on the Cattel and Corn upon a Sabbath day.</p>
            <p>Particularly, I ſerve inhibition this day on the Table of our Lord, againſt all the Men and Women in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that wittingly and willingly are Enemies to the perſecuted and diſtreſſed Cauſe, and work of God this day, what ever it be, be it Prelacy, be it Snpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, or be it arbitrary Government, be it any thing that the People of God are ſuffering for this day, for it's ſad ſince the buſineſs is come to ſuch a length in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that their is a ſtated quarrel between Chriſts and Antichriſts backing, and that this controverſie has come to that length, we have ſo many Heads ſtanding on Poles on the account of it in <hi>Air</hi> and in other places of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when there are ſo many in Priſon upon this account, and the Enemies have imbrued their hands ſo dreadfully in the Blood of the Saints of God; you muſt now ſide your ſelves, you muſt Liſt your ſelves, either on Chriſts Side, or the Devils, now any of you that have complyed with the Enemy, to ſtrengthen their hands, either by taking the Declaration or the Oath of Supremacy, or any the black bands, that have gone up and down the Land, any that has been troublers of the People of God, and complyers with the Prelates and Curates, if ye reſolve to go on longer in theſe courſes, go to their Camp and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180311:7"/>ſeek your Food, and come not Enemies in heart to this perſecuted Table of the Lord in the Wilderneſs. In the name of the great God, I diſcharge you as ye would not incurr the damnation of your Souls, and as ye would not be crucifiers of the Son of God, and bring that upon your ſelves which you cannot eaſily take off. But now upon the other hand, leaſt that ſome poor thing ſhould be kept back, leaſt they ſhould hold back, and that their ſhould be a ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch, that the Bowels of Chriſt are yearning on this day, therefore we have this to ſay, be who yee will that is here, that deſired this day to bid adue to your Luſts, and will Sin no more, that is grieved in your hearts for the Evils ye have done to Chriſt, and that is reſolving to live to him, and to be for him hereafter; that is, reſolving to eſpouſe his cauſe, and to bide by him upon all hazards over all difficulties; be what you will, we invite you here to be ſharers of this Feaſt of Fat things, and Wine on the Leas well refined, if thy Fingers were reeking with the Blood of the Saints, if that now be thy exerciſe, if thou reſolve to be ſo no more, come away; if thou had been a Witch, and had made an actual Portion with the Devil, and would break the bargain now with the Devil, and would make a new bargain with our King Chriſt, come away if thou hath been guilty of Theft and Murder, and never ſo many abominations, if now thou be reforming, and if this be thy exerciſe this day woes me, I have ſo long dwelt in Sin and ſojourned in the Tents of wickedneſs; our Lords Bowels yearns on you this day, and in the name of our Lord, we invite you all to come forward; come away poor thing, what ever has been thy ſad miſcarriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, come away, and thy Burden on thy Back to the Table of the Lord, that before witneſſes thou may give up thy name to the Son of God; and here we are to take thee as a bond-ſervant, and to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thee in his name: now dear Friends, lay ye the buſineſs to heart, and think not that you muſt come and Mock him, think not that you muſt come and profane the Table of our bleſſed Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but let all your debates be at an end; now, O let all your confuſions be at an end, now, but if thou ſhould come with confuſion in thy Spirit, come as thou art, only let this be between Chriſt and you, that henceforth ye are roſolved to be the Lords for better and worſe. Look on him, now tell me how would yee look on him, if yee ſaw him the day, would yee have a Sight of him;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180311:8"/>O Men and Women, then he took up a peice of Bread in the one hand, and the Cup of Wine in the other, and ſaid, come, come, Sirs, ſee yee him, now behold your King, behold him that was dead and is alive; behold him that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> behold him that is now up above the Clouds, ſitting at the thrown of grace, pleading on your behalf; there is a ſight, the greater ye will not get in the kind of it in the World, yee will not get the like of it till yee come to Heaven, and ſee him in another manner of way, how ſee yee him the day his Body all peirced, his Body in one place, and his Blood in another; when ye are ſound in Limb and Lith, he is all tattered, and he is drawn a ſunder, and your Blood is in your Veins; behold Chriſts Blood is one way, and his Body another: O! how comes it to paſs that our Bleſſed Lord and Mediator was ſeen in ſuch away? it was not becauſe enemies was able to Maſter him, but it was that yee might get good of him the day, and yee could not have fed on him, except he had been wounded; now, now, would ye know how this comes to paſs, that our bleſſed Lord has gotten ſuch wounds, and that his wounds appears in two places, the day would ye know how he has gotten theſe two wounds, the day Juſtice gave him one blow for the Sin of the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe they had ſinned, Juſtice ſays, they muſt die, Chriſt ſays rather, give me a blow on the Cheek, though it ſhould ding all the Fleſh from the Bones, well ſays Juſtice, muſt it be ſo, then Juſtice gives him one wound, know yee how he has gotten another wound? he has gotten it for the Sin of the Gentiles, and among the reſt, for the Communicants of <hi>Carrick;</hi> this day it is for you, Juſtice ſays, they muſt die, wrath muſt be upon <hi>Carrick,</hi> and wrath muſt be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the profeſſors of <hi>Scotland,</hi> except the Son of God take a blow and wound on the behalf, it is on this account he ſuffers, and for your ſake he takes it, yee ſee now his Body one way, and his Blood another; and if yee had looked on him in the Garden, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very drop of Sweat was like a drop of Blood; think yee that he come eaſily by the bargain, indeed yee have come eaſily by the bargain: O profeſſors of <hi>Carrick,</hi> yee may Sing the Victory is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed to your hand, that the great King procured, is brought to your hand, and let me ask one queſtion of you, when yee ſaw your Mediator ſo wounded, and in ſuch a caſe, what would ye think of them? the day that would call you, that yee will give him a wound,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180311:8"/>the day to all that he has gotten, and that yee will give him a wound that ſhall be ſorer, and be ſadder to him, then all the wounds he ſuffered; he is content to be tattered for your ſakes, but he is not content to be tattered by you; he is not content when he is pauncing his wounds for you, that ye ſhould give him a wound more; do ye ſuffer in your hearts to crucifie him a freſh? I confeſs ye may think on us as Fools and diſtracted Perſons, and ſay, what need we preſent a cup of Wine, and a peice of bread, could it not be done in another way? indeed, if our Lord had not appointed it himſelf, we had been in the dark, and had carried as diſtracted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, woe to them that comes in with their Surpluſe, and corner Caps, and Oil and Salt, and all the reſt of their Ceremonies, and theſe things that Chriſt Jeſus never warranted nor appointed, but that yee may ſee, and be convinced, that thoſe things is not our devices, but the appointment of God himſelf, we ſhall read the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to you, and let you ſee the warrant that he himſelf hath given, that he hath ſet down in the Evangeliſts, but we ſhall read that which is ſet down in the 1 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 11 chap. 2 ver. For I have received of the Lord, that which alſo I delivered to you, that the Lord Jeſus in the ſame night: wherein he was betrayed took bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>After he had given thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sirs, ye ſee that he can ſet apart what Elements he pleaſes, and can make them indeed ſignificant ceremonies and pleadges to purpoſe, to be clear ſymptoms and remembrances of a bargain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and us, and to be the evidences that we ſhall not want what we ſtand in need of coming to him in the right manner. Now then, know ye when this was, it was in the Night wherein he was Betrayed; he caſt a copy to us, and according to that Pattern that he gave us, that is, the thing we have to do, the day to take and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute theſe Elements to you, to be the Pledges <hi>Carrick</hi> is eſpouſed to Chriſt, and that it may be a Covenant that ſhall not be broken: indeed there is a difference between Chriſts work and your work, well could he handle it, and well could he go about the work, but we amble the buſineſs, he could make it effectual by his own power, we cannot do that, but we muſt come as far benn as we can, and we muſt put it over the Maſters hand, that he will give the Bleſſing, and that he will fit us, and that he will fit the work; and O if you had one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180311:9"/>heart the day you would concur and wreſtle for a Bleſſing on the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, that it may be for our advantage the day, let us go and ſeek the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tabe Firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sirs, are you right, is there any thing yet to do, he is ready for you, his bowels yearns after you, his arms are open, the day ye have ſeen him, we cannot tell what that ſight has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced on your Souls. O! have ye not bleed at the ſight of ſuch a one; could ye not be content to have born ſome of the blows that were laid on him; think ye not but ye could have given your cheek to the ſmiter; when they took the hair of his cheek, could ye not have been content to have taken a ſhare of it, that is not all, it is not only a ſight of Chriſt, crying, <hi>Behold me, behold me,</hi> but a ſight that ye may come and ſee; and here it is, <hi>Eat O Friends, drink ye drink abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.</hi> O beloved only, if ye be ready only, if ye be ready, tell us your anſwer, are ye ready or not? is there any that would riſe from the Table and would ſpare a while: yet if ye be not ready, we cannot help it, for he is ready. In that Night that he was betrayed, he took bread and brake it, and gave his Diſciples, and ſaid, <hi>Take ye eat ye, this is my Body which is broke for you, do this in remembrance of me.</hi> Now, we give it you on your Peril, and as ye ſhall anſwer to that God, ſo carry in the buſineſs, but in part we deſire to be free of your Blood, and we pronounce our being free of your Blood, and he has dealt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly with you, ſee that ye deal not deceitfully and treacherouſly with him, but it is not a dry morſel that he prepares, there is more, it is not meat that he entertains his Gueſts with, but drink alſo in like manner; after Supper he took the Cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave it to his Diſciples, and ſaid, <hi>Drink ye all of it, and divide it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, &amp;c.</hi> Here, here have your thoughts above, and be taken up with Meditation, ye muſt remember it is one qualification of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, and in the time that ye are about the work, apprehend ye ſee him hanging on the Croſs, and ye keeping the Blood that drops from him, that that Blood may waſh away all your Iniquities, that ye nay be cleanſed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for there is no other way whereby ye can be preſented ſpotleſs and blameleſs before the Lord; there is vertue here to Cure all your diſtempers, and to make you perfectly clean if thou were as filthy as <hi>Lazarus,</hi> it is he that will do your turn; now, now ye have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180311:9"/>him among your hands, ſee how ye will guide him once again; think with your ſelves what is your opinion of your noble Husband; now what think you of a Marriage day now? what think ye of it to be ſhaking hands with ſuch a Prince, and with ſuch a Captain, or now would ye be content to quit your part of him before ye riſe from the Table, or will ye take your old Trade? will the Drunkard go to the Ale-houſe? will the Swearer Swear? will the Unclean perſon conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue Unclean? will ye prefer the world to him? what if a new Hoaſt of <hi>Highlanders</hi> ſhould come in among you, and ſhould preſs you to take the Bond, what would ye do? know in that Night <hi>Peter</hi> took the Communion, he bant and Swore he knew not Chriſt; what if ſome of you that ſits at the Table ſhall lift up the heel againſt the Son of God before the Son go down, ye ſhould eat this Bread with careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and drink this Drink with aſtoniſhment, for it is hard to ſay, what a Plague and Curſe goes down with it; what ſhall I tell you Sirs, the ground is holy, the Maſter of the Feaſt is holy, but all the Gueſts is unholy, a beatifical Captain, a beautiful Maſter, beautiful Priviledges, and beautiful Ordinances, but O a black Bride, a black Bride for him to take by the hand; but how comes this to paſs, that ſome of you, yea all of you, that were a few days ago ſhaking hands with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that a few days ago had your Necks in the Devils yoke; how comes it that ye quit that bargain, and come to kiſs the Son of God? what has allured you to come from your own Camp? what has made you to quit the world? might nor the ſweet world that ye were in, have allured you to ſtay with it? what has come on <hi>Scotland</hi> this day to fleighter after an unſeen and unknown Chriſt? what means the Husband to come away and quit the Wife? what means the Wife to come away and quit the Husband? and what means the Barnes to leave the Parents, and the Parents to leave the Barnes? and what means the Husbandman to give the Cow, and the Barneyeards their leave, and they are come to the Fields to imbrace the Son of God; but it may be ſome thinks this is not their Errand, but ſince ye are come out of the World, and has turned your back on it, that that I would ſay is not only to welcome you in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but to tell you, that the broad bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> hangs over your head, the day the broad bleſſing of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> hangs over your heads the day, and ye ſhall not looſe your reward, your Maſter is able to do your turn, and to bear your expdnces; it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180311:10"/>may be after this, ye ſhall meet with the Croſs, but ye ſhall have that that ſhall make the Croſs ſweet to you, that ye ſhall not ill-will your Enemies in the midſt of it. Now even your hearts be right with him, as his heart is right with you, at leaſt as long as ye make the bargain, and give him the hand, and ſay, <hi>I take Chriſt for my Saviour, O be not dealing deceitfully.</hi> Now Chriſt is yours, and Heaven is yours, come after what will, come death, come life, it ſhall never part you and him, even much joy may ye have of your new Husband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion after the Tables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe the day wears to one end, and for ſome other reaſons we are neceſſitate to break off, we hope there is none that has prepared themſelves for this that need offend, that they have not been admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this Table, this is a great priviledge, but folk may win to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven though they do not formally partake of this ordinance, and where is a faltable appetite and deſire, he accepts of the will for the deed; but now my friends, ye have been witneſſes this day of, and exalted Chriſt after his Death and Burial, ye are they before whoſe eyes he has been ſet out Crucified among you, ye are they among whom he has done great things, and has lifted up his Banner, and I hope there is ſome here that will reckon ſuch a day as this well worth a Priſon, well worth a Croſs, and it may garr <hi>Carrick,</hi> and the places about forget that miſery that the Hoſt of the <hi>Highlanders</hi> did to ſee God undermine them, and to ſee God diſappoint the deſigns of Enemies, while they thought by theſe Savages, to make us turn our back on this cauſe, and to make the Countrey-ſide rid of that work that they call Conventicles, God has diſperſed them, and covered a Table over again, and has brought together an Aſſembly greater then any that has been here before. O what ſhall we ſay of the bounty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendency of our God, it is like ſome will be angry at us for this days work? we will be charged with Rebellion and Sedition, but ſuch a Feaſt as this is worth the ſuffering Reproach, as well as other things to ſuffer; but now this day the three Perſons in the Trinity is witneſs, Angels is witneſs, and that Son is a witneſs, that there is a Bargain drawn up between God and you, the Contract has been fairly laid out before you, you need not now come and ſay, if ye meet with a Trouble, and if ye meet with a Croſs, that ye have met with a diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment in this buſineſs, the beſt and the worſt has been laid out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, it has been told you, the Croſs waits on you, and it has been <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
